Inventory of the Houstater Family Papers 1842-1941
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Houstater Family Papers 1842-1941
Special Collections Research Center
01/Mss. Acc. 2009.264
1.00
Papers of the Houstater Family, primarily of Henry Houstater (1837-1862) and Harriet (Hattie) Houstater (1842-1931) of New York State. Collection was held by Harriet Houstater. After her death, her sister Sarah Houstater owned it.
Houstater, Henry F., 1837-1862; Houstater, Harriet, 1842-1931 arrangement
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
The materials were acquired by Special Collections Research Center on 06/08/2009.
Biographical Note
Henry F. Houstater was born on 24 June, 1837 in Cambria TWP, Niagara, NY and died 29 October, 1862 in Sandy Hook, Washington, MD. He was buried at Mount View Cemetery, Pekin, Niagara, NY. His father was Jacob "Isiah" Houstater, b. 4 August, 1802 and his mother Belinda GOULD, b. 2 February, 1809 in NY.
On September 18, 1861, he enlisted, at Lockport; mustered in as private, Battery M, 1st Regiment, Light Artillery, October 14,1861, to serve three years; he was appointed corporal, October 14, 1861; sergeant, February 6, 1862; and died, October 29, 1862, at Sandy Hook, Md. Politically, he affiliated with the Democratic party.
Scope and Contents
Papers of the Houstater Family, primarily of Henry Houstater (1837-1862) and Harriet (Hattie) Houstater (1842-1931) of New York State. Collection was held by Harriet Houstater. After her death, her sister Sarah Houstater owned it.
Collection includes the papers of Henry F. Houstater, a Democrat who enlisted in the Union Army in 1861. Also contains the papers of several Houstater family members. Henry F. Houstater's papers (1840s-1862) include political speeches and literary manuscripts written before the Civil War. During the war, Henry wrote and received several letters and he also wrote several political essays and produced a handwritten newspaper, the Camp Barry Herald.
Other family members' papers consists of correspondence and financial documents.
Arrangement of Materials
Organized into ten series: Series 1: Wills & Related Papers, Series 2: Deeds & Land Surveys, Series 3: Taxes & Payments, Series 4:Bonds, Series 5: Bills, Miscellaneous Documents, Series 6: Mortgages & Payments, Series 7: Letters to/from Houstaters, Series 8: Houstater Newspapers, Series 9: Camp Barry Herald, Series 10: Henry Houstater’s Writings
Additional Information
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Correspondence; Newspapers
Geographic Name:
United States--History--Civil War--Niagra County, NY
Topical Term:
New York (State)--Social life and customs; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Personal narratives; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Sources; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Detailed Description of the Collection
  Series 1: Wills & Related Papers
- Wills & Related Papers, 1857-1938
  Contains several wills of deceased family members Jacob Houstater, Chauncey Keep, Frances E. Lord and Genevieve Pike. Some are official legal documents, another is handwritten.
  Series 2: Deeds & Land Surveys
- Deeds & Land Surveys, 1836-1943
  Documents related to lands owned by the Houstaters (Jacob Houstater and Martin Wolfe).
  Series 3: Taxes & Payments
- Taxes & Payments, 1842-1935
  City documents regarding the Houstaters taxes. Many tax receipts from Jacob Houstater's property are included and they range from 1842 to 1888.
  Series 4: Bonds
- Bonds, 1859-1923
  Several bond documents related to the Houstater family including Harriet Houstater's own Bond paperwork.
  Series 5: Bills & Misc.
- Bills & Misc., 1862-1931
  Various bills related to the Houstaters are included. A receipt for the transport of Henry's Houstater's body as well as an itemized bill for his funerary expenses is included.
  Series 6: Mortgages & Payments
- Mortgages & Payments, 1862-1944
  Mortgages for the Houstaters and receipts of payment. Includes Jacob Houstater and Harriet Houstater as well as families related to the Houstaters.
  Series 7: Letters to/from Houstaters
- Letters to/from Houstaters, 1857-1888
  Letters from Henry Houstater at Camp Barry to his family and letters to him during the Civil War are included. Telegrams and postal cards included as well. One particular telegrams bears the news of Henry's death to the family. Harriet Houstater also wrote a love letter entitled "What Hattie Thinks of Billy."
  Series 8: Houstater Newspapers
- Houstater Newspapers, March 13,1862- June 18, 1864
  Newspapers collected by the Houstaters during the Civil War. The majority are affiliated with the Democratic party. Papers consist of issues dated 3-13, 3-28, 4-7, 4-9, 9-8, 10-1, 11-18 from 1862 of the Lockport Daily Union as well as an issue of Niagra Democrat and Union from 1864 and two from the Lockport Chronicle in 1862.
  Series 9: Camp Barry Herald
- Camp Barry Herald, 1861-1862
  The Camp Barry Herald was a small paper produced by Henry Houstater. The pieces included are handwritten and feature news from the Civil War, poetry and art. One article recounts the death of a comrade in battle.
  Series 10: Henry's Writings
- Henry's Writings
  Many of these do not include dates. This folder contains various political essays with a clearly Democratic affiliation. One expressed dissatisfaction with the election of Lincoln and called for the election of Stephen Douglas.
  Subseries 8: Newspaper Clippings
- Newspaper Clippings, Unknown (8)
  Clippings from various newspapers. Includes poetry from the Civil War era, dietary information and a small piece on Colonel Caleb Hopkins.